Guide to the Percy Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Percy family papers
1760-1822
OSB MSS 88
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, covers, and other documents chiefly from members of the Percy family to members of the Davidson family, disbound from album assembled by Thomas Davidson, Jr. Includes routine business and social letters from the first three Dukes of Northumberland to Thomas Davidson and Thomas Davidson, Jr.; letters from Elizabeth Percy to Martha Davidson; one letter by Thomas Percy; and various autographs and seals.
Davidson, Thomas, fl. ca. 1800
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1969. For further information, please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
I. Hugh Percy (formerly Smithson), 1st Duke of Northumberland, 1715-1786
Hugh Smithson, fourth baronet of Stanwick in Yorkshire, married the heiress to the Percy title and estates in 1740 over the objections of her family. In 1750, shortly after her succession as Baroness Percy suo jure, Hugh Smithson took the surname Percy by Act of Parliament and was seated in the House of Lords as Earl of Northumberland. He was created Duke in 1766 with the support of William Pitt.
Northumberland was active in politics for over thirty years. He instituted many agricultural improvements on the Percy estates, reclaiming land and rebuilding laborers' cottages, and developed highly profitable coal mines. He renovated Alnwick Castle, hiring Robert Adam as architect and designer, was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society, and was a founding Trustee of the British Museum.
The couple had two sons and one daughter, Lady Elizabeth, who died unmarried. In addition, Northumberland had several natural children. His son James Smithson, born in France to Elizabeth Keate Macie in 1765, was trained as a scientist at Oxford and died in Genoa in 1829, leaving the estate that eventually became the founding bequest of the Smithsonian Institution.
Lady Elizabeth Percy, Duchess of Northumberland, died in 1776. Hugh Percy, Duke of Northumberland, died on June 6, 1786.
II. Hugh Percy, (sometime Smithson), 2nd Duke of Northumberland, 1742-1817
Eldest son of the first Duke, Hugh Smithson assumed the surname of Percy by Act of Parliament along with his father in 1750. He entered the Army in 1759 and in 1764 married Lady Anne Stuart, daughter of Lord Bute. He served with distinction at the Battle of Lexington and was named Lieutenant-General of the Army in America early in 1777, but was recalled from command after many disputes with General Howe. He continued his military career, however, taking command of the Percy yeomanry regiment in 1798 and a colonelcy in the horse-guards in 1806.
Northumberland was granted a divorce in Parliament from Lady Anne in 1779 on the grounds of her adultery; he immediately married Frances Julia Burrell, with whom he had three daughters and two sons. He continued his father's agricultural improvements, and when corn prices fell after 1815, he reduced his rents by twenty-five percent; his tenants built a monument to him in gratitude. He held twice-weekly gatherings at Alnwick Castle, inviting tenants and local tradespeople. The second Duke of Northumberland died suddenly "of rheumatic gout" in July 1817. His widow died in May, 1820.
III. Hugh Percy, 3rd Duke of Northumberland, 1785-1847
Hugh Percy, eldest son of the second Duke, was educated at St. John's College, Cambridge and elected M.P. for Buckingham and for Westminster in 1806. While in Parliament he proposed a bill to abolish slavery in the British colonies, but it failed. In 1807 he took his seat in the House of Lords as Baron Percy. Ten years later he succeeded his father as Duke of Northumberland. He married Lady Charlotte Florentia Clive, who was for some years Governess to the future Queen Victoria. The couple had no children.
Northumberland was Ambassador Extraordinary to France at the coronation of Charles X in 1825. In January 1829 he was appointed Governor-General of Ireland, shortly before the passage of the Catholic Relief Bill, and was recalled when the ministry of the Duke of Wellington fell in November 1830. He was elected Chancellor of Cambridge in 1840, a post he held until his death at Alnwick Castle on February 12, 1847.
Scope and Contents
The Percy Family Papers consist of letters, covers, and a few other papers, most sent to members of the Davidson family by several members of the Percy (Smithson) family, particularly the first three Dukes of Northumberland. The papers span the dates 1760-1822 and were originally assembled into an autograph album by Thomas Davidson, Jr., Esq. of Newcastle on Tyne, who held at least two patronage positions in the grant of the Dukes, including Distributor of Stamps for Northumberland. The album was disassembled in 1969 and the correspondence received its present arrangement; other papers were apparently kept in their original order. The papers have been organized into two series: I. Correspondence; and II. Other Album Pages.
Series I, Correspondence, is housed in folders 1-97 and contains letters and covers, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. About half of the items in the series are unaccompanied covers addressed to various members of the Davidson family, mounted on album pages, some annotated by Davidson. The remainder are almost entirely brief business and social notes from the Dukes of Northumberland to Thomas Davidson and Thomas Davidson, Jr.
While the letters are largely routine, the correspondence as a whole sheds light on the strong and well-tended connections between the Percy family and the recipients of their patronage. Topics include payments and letters to be forwarded by Davidson for them; local committee meetings, village and manor court schedules, and appointments; social calls and invitations to public receptions at Alnwick Castle; congratulations on the birth of children and condolences on deaths; and the frequent absences of the Dukes and their family members in London.
A letter of February 6, 1781 conveys Northumberland's endorsement of Thomas Davidson, Jr.'s nomination as Distributor of Stamps. Letters by the second Duke of Northumberland also discuss Davidson's appointment as Clerk of the Lieutenancy of the County and various militia matters during the Napoleonic Wars. An 1816 letter concerns shipping arrangements for a portrait of the Duke by Thomas Phillips, which "has been much admired in London by the connoisseurs." Box 2, folder 86 contains four letters from his sister, Lady Elizabeth Percy, to Martha Davidson, containing family news and expressions of homesickness for Alnwick Castle.
Series II, Other Album Pages, is located in folders 98-107 and arranged in original album order. Contents include a printed copy of the Davidson crest; locks of hair; a recipe for rheumatism medicine; and detached autographs and seals. There are two printed items: a copy of the popular facsimile of the last letter of Queen Marie Antoinette with accompanying printed translation; and a broadside "Monody on the Death" of Frances Julia, Dowager Duchess of Northumberland, attributed to "M.H." of "Ladies' Academy, Wearmouth."
Nobility -- Great Britain -- Autographs; Patronage, Political; Northumberland (England) -- History; Davidson, Martha; Davidson, Thomas, 1722-1781; Davidson, Thomas, fl. ca. 1800; Northumberland, Algernon Percy, Duke of, 1792-1865; Northumberland, Hugh Percy, Duke of, 1712-1786; Northumberland, Hugh Percy, Duke of, 1742-1817; Northumberland, Hugh Percy, Duke of, 1785-1847; Percy, Elizabeth, Lady; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811; Percy family
- Correspondence, 1760-1822; Series I; 0.51; (1.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - HAMILTON, EUPHEMIA HAMILTON, DUCHESS OF, 1786-1859
    - ALS to Martha Davidson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - HEARD, ISAAC, 1730-1822
    - ALS to the Duke of Northumberland (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - LEFEVRE, ----
    - ALS to Henry Reveley, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, CHARLOTTE FLORENTIA (CLIVE) PERCY
    [DUCHESS OF, 1787-1866]
    - ALS to Martha Davidson; London, 1820 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, FRANCES JULIA (BURELL) PERCY
    [DUCHESS OF, 1752-1820]
    - 2 ALS to Martha Davidson; Clifton, 1789 Oct 6, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson, Jr., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - With: letter to Mrs. Davidson, n.d.
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, HUGH PERCY, DUKE OF, 1715-1786
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Northumberland House, 1760 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1765 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS in third person to Thomas Davidson; Northumberland House, 1772 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - LS to Thomas Davidson; Northumberland House, 1781 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      T. Davidson, Jr., to be Distributor of Stamps. In the hand of Thomas Percy
    - ALS in third person to Thomas Davidson, [1783?] Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Bath, 1783 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to John Lowes; Bath, 1783 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2 LS to William Lowes; Northumberland House, 1774 May, Jun (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Concerning a forthcoming election; in the hand of Thomas Percy
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, HUGH PERCY, DUKE OF, 1742-1817
    - ALS to John Davidson; Syon [London], 1786 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cover to John Davidson; Alnwick, 1788 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to John Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1804 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - ALS to John Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1809 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Stanwick, 1783 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Stanwick, 1783 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Stanwick, 1784 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Northumberland House, 1787 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1804 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1805 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1805 Sep (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1805 -- 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1808 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1808 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1808 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1810 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1810 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1811 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1812 Jan 12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1812 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Cover to Miss Davidson; Alnwick, 1813 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      With note, "Please remember me kindly to Bolby."
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - ALS fragment to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1814 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - ALS (fragment) to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1815 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Aug 14 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1816 -- 28 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1817 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - ALS and cover to Thomas Davidson; Northumberland House, 1817 May, Jul (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient; Northumberland House, 1787 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - NORTHUMBERLAND, HUGH PERCY, DUKE OF, 1785-1847
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1807 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson, Ferry Bridge, 1807 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Ferry Bridge, 1807 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Durham, [1808?] (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1808 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1810 Jul 9 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1812 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; York, 1816 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1816 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      With note, "If Mr. Davidson should not value the enclosed letter..."
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1816 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1816 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Worcester, 1817 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; London, 1818 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Cover with ALS fragment verso to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1818 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1818 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1818 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Cover with ALS fragment verso to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1818 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1818 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Cover to the Duchess of Northumberland; London, 1819 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1820 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1820 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1821 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1822 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick, 1822 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - ALS in third person to Thomas Davidson; Forcett, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - PERCY, ISABEL ELIZABETH, LADY, D. 1820
    - 4 ALS to Martha Davidson, 1808-17 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Office copy of her will, Little Syon, Isleworth, 1820 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - PERCY, JULIA, LADY, 1784-1812
    - 2 ALS to Martha Davidson; Alnwick Castle and Northumberland House, 1806, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - PERCY, THOMAS, 1729-1811
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Alnwick Castle, 1780 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - POWIS, HENRIETTA ANTONIA, COUNTESS OF, 1758-1830
    - ALS to Martha Davidson, 1822 Jul 10 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - REDESDALE, JOHN FREEMAN-MITFORD, BARON, 1748-1830
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London, 1819 Dec 3 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Batsford, 1820 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Cover to Thomas Davidson; London [?], 1820 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - SMITH, D.C.
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson, 1814 Oct 7 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - SPEARMAN, R.
    - ALS to Thomas Davidson; Eachwick Hall, 1816 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - ALS to unidentified; Stanwick, 1818 Nov 14 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Cover to D. of Northumberland, 1820 Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 97)
- Other Album Pages, 1819-1820; Series II; 0.13; (.5 box)
  Series II, Other Album Pages, is arranged in original album order.
  - Davidson crest and autograph (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Shakespeare passage copied by Lady Agnes Percy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Locks of hair of Julia Duchess of Northumberland, Lady Elizabeth Percy, and Lady Julia Percy (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - "Fac-simile of the Letter of the late Queen of France to Madame Elizabeth...," Westley and Parrish, printers, Strand. (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - "The Signatures in Autographs and Seals of," pasted collection with entries in Davidson's hand (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Recipe for medicine for rheumatism, 1819 Jul 30 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - "Monody, on the death of Her Grace, Frances Julia, Dowager Duchess of Northumberland," J.K. Pollock, printer, North Shields., 1820 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Autographs of Hugh Percy, 1st Duke of Northumberland, Hugh Percy, 2nd Duke of Northumberland, and Hugh Percy, 3rd Duke of Northumberland (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - 2 mounted covers to "Earl Percy," Alnwick and [n.p.], [180?], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Printed material and genealogical notes (Box 2, Folder 107)